Julián Roa Rozo October 7, 1995

julian_roa_rozo@hotmail.com j.roa10@uniandes.edu.co +57 300-5430682 Bogotá D.C Colombia

Profile

I am an economist interested in macroeconomics, public policy, and econometrics. I have bachelor studies in Economics from Universidad Nacional de Colombia. I also have a master's degree in Economics from Universidad de los Andes. In Econometría Consultores, I have participated as coordinator and research assistant in impact evaluation, public policy evaluation, and macroeconomic and sectoral analysis. While at Banco de la República de Colombia, I assisted in research projects in the Research Unit.

Work experience

Econometría Consultores

March 2018 – Today

Project coordinator - June 2022 to today

I have assisted as coordinator in three studies:

- Diseñar y desarrollar una evaluación de operaciones y resultados en torno a los procesos, componentes y objetivos de la Modalidad 1000 Días para Cambiar el Mundo, con el fin de analizar la eficacia de la Modalidad y generar recomendaciones de mejora - ICBF
- Consultoría para un estudio de mercado del sector postal panameño BID
- Elaboración de informes mensuales de análisis económico y político del país, con proyecciones sectoriales Banco Patria

Research assistant - March 2018 - June 2022

As research assistant I've participated in the following studies:

- Modelamiento de los efectos macroeconómicos de la transición a la economía circular para Latinoamérica CEPAL (See link)
- Estudio de factibilidad de una empresa Naviera de la Armada Nacional Armada Nacional de Colombia
- Estudio de evolución y prospectiva de la industria de comunicaciones frente a la crisis generada por el COVID-19 observatorio de inversión en comunicaciones Comisión de Regulación de Comunicaciones (See link)
- Evaluación de resultados e impacto del Programa 40.000 Primeros Empleos Departamento Nacional de Planeación (See link)

Banco de la República Research Unit Research asistant

January 2017 – December 2017

- Gómez-Pineda, J.G. (2020) Volatility spillovers and the global financial cycle across economies: Evidence from a global semi-structural model, Economic Modelling.
- Gómez, J. G. (2018) A well-timed raise in inflation target, Borradores de Economía, núm. 1042, Banco de la República

• Julio, J. M.; Gómez, J. G.; Hernández, M. D. (2017). La inflación de los precios rígidos en Colombia, Borradores de Economía, núm. 1007, Banco de la República

Education

Universidad de los Andes

2019-I - 2021-I

Master in Economics - PEG

GPA: 4.34

Thesis: Spillovers de la política monetaria no covencional de los países avanzados hacia

América Latina

Thesis director: Javier G. Gómez Pineda

Thesis grade: 5.0

Universidad Nacional de Colombia - Sede Bogotá

2013 - 2017

Economist GDP: 4,4

Publications

- Gómez-Pineda, J.G. & Roa-Rozo, J. (2022) A univariate output gap model with potential output hysteresis. Borradores de Economía, num. 1230, Banco de la República.
- Roa-Rozo, J. (2022) We should reject the natural rate hypothesis: Evidence from high and middle-income economies. Accepted on the LACEA-LAMES 2022 annual meeting (Perú)
- Roa-Rozo, J. (2021) Spillovers de la política monetaria no convencional de los pases avanzados hacia América Latina. (Julio 2021) Documento CEDE No. 34 (See link)
- Pulido-Mahecha, K. y Roa-Rozo, J. (2021) Histéricas pero convergentes: el comportamiento de las tasas de desempleo en Colombia en *Colombia: Algunos problemas de hoy vistos por los jóvenes Desempleo, educación y paz.* Academia Colombiana de Ciencias Económicas. Capítulo de libro.
- Franco Hernandez, C. y Roa Rozo, J. (2018) El valor agregado de la universidades públicas en el rendimiento académico: Una relación no homogénea. Econografos FCE-UN. (See link)
- Roa Rozo, J. (2017) ¿Hubo contagio financiero en las crisis financieras recientes? Una aplicación DCC-M-GARCH para Argentina, Brasil, Colombia y Estados Unidos. Econografos FCE-UN. (See link)

Press articles

- ¿Por qué Colombia crece tanto? (See link) -Journal La República, 2022.
- Implicaciones de la guerra Rusia Ucrania (See link) Journal La República, 2022.
- Economía circular: enfoque que genera rentabilidad (See link) -Journal La República, 2022. Joint with Óscar Rodriguez, Guillermo Rudas, Maria Paula Rivera,
- The 2021 surge in inflation: A look at sticky prices (See link) VOX-EU, 2021. Joint with Javier Gómez Pineda and Juan Manuel Julio

- Crecimiento económico y el CONPES de reactivación (See link) -Journal La República, 2021.
- Seguiremos en 2020 hasta junio (See link) -Journal La República, 2021.
- Entre la curva Nike y la curva W (See link) -Journal La República, 2020.
- ¿Curva V? (See link) -Journal La República, 2020.
- Las medidas extremas para tiempos extremos (See link) -Journal La República, 2020.
- El coronavirus ataca el pulmón de la economía colombiana (See link) -Journal La República, 2020.

Rewards

XVI Concurso Nacional de Ponencias Jesús Antonio Bejarano

2017

Winner A category

Paper: Histéricas pero convergentes: el comportamiento de las tasas de desempleo en Colombia

Universidad Nacional de Colombia - Sede Bogotá Scholarship

2014-I and 2014-II

Software

Office (Word, Excel and Powerpoint), Stata, MATLAB (Iris and Dynare), R, Arcgis and Latex

Languages

Proficient in English and French.

References

Mauricio Olivera 317-4343043

Economist

CFO Universidad de los Andes

Javier G. Gómez Pineda 321-2702541

Economist

Senior Economist at Banco de la Republica